<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Beer on David John Baker</title>
    <link>/tags/beer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Beer on David John Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 David John Baker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/beer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part IV</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-iv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-iv/</guid>
      <description>Since this is my last post in the beer review series, I’ll keep this short and sweet in terms of analysis. Having done all of this, I do have a few reflections I would like to share after doing the One-Size-Fits-All-Data-Science Interview that I have included at the end.
Our final question to answer is:
 Lastly, if I typically enjoy a beer due to its aroma and appearance, which beer style should I try?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part III</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-datascientist-part-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-datascientist-part-iii/</guid>
      <description>Two questions down, two to go! For the third post I’ll explore the question:
 Which of the factors (aroma, taste, appearance, palate) are most important in determining the overall quality of a beer?
 Whereas the posts before were questions on sorting data, this is our first attempt to make some statistical models. In this case, we’re going to be doing a bit of regression modeling.
There are a couple of ways to tackle this problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part II</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on from my earlier post, I’m now looking to tackle the question:
 If you had to pick 3 beers to recommend using only this data, which would you pick?
 This is a pretty open ended question, which is kind of fun. I also don’t really have a ton of experience (yet!) in recommendation systems, though I have done a little reading here or there on it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>