<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>David John Baker on David John Baker</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in David John Baker on David John Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 David John Baker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium on Open Science</title>
      <link>/talk/smpc-openscience-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/smpc-openscience-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is happening in a student’s mind when they perform melodic dictation?</title>
      <link>/talk/smpc-comp-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/smpc-comp-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing Career Diversity</title>
      <link>/post/embracing-career-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/embracing-career-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;things-are-different-now&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Things Are Different Now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, first-blog-post-since-I-defended-my-Ph.D!
It’s wild to think that after five or so years (between starting the the MSc. and the final Ph.D. defense), I am finally done with graduate school.
There are no more exams, no more term deadlines, and no more giant documents to write.
The last few months felt like quite the pressure cooker between writing everything up, flying back to defend, then doing a bit of travel.
And now after the sprint at the end of the marathon, it’s finally over.
It kind of feels like a scene out of a movie where the soundtrack builds to a climax, but then it all just goes silent.
I feel a bit caught in suspended animation and have a lot of thoughts swirling around and no structure to place them within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what’s a boy with a lot of feelings in 2019 to do?
Start a podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just kidding, the last thing the world needs is another dude telling you his opinions about the world on a podcast.
I am not starting a podcast.
But I do want to blog more.
It’s something I personally find very helpful to do myself and have found reading other’s blogs to be &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; helpful.
In this post, I want to do a bit of self-justification and mindless rambling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;bigsat&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;bigsat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as noted above, I’m finally done with the Ph.D. (Yippe!)
It was a trudge to say the least.
Not only was it a lot of work, but living in a work environment for a few years as an intellectual underling is not exactly great for your self esteem.
The hours and pay were not great (if you think about the Ph.D. like a job), but more importantly, the grind of graduate school is not sustainable.
The rate that I was working in the months leading up to my dissertation submission consumed every part of my life.
Having spent so much time on my #bigsit and all the graduate school that lead up to that, I also was starting to feel a deeper dread that large portions of my life were passing me by and I was loosing time that I could not get back.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The good news is that retrospectively I don’t regret any of it.
As a result, I have a dissertation that I am very proud of on many levels.
I’ll be blogging about that soon as well.
But I also think that it is important to acknowledge all these thoughts and feelings and reflect on them.
And one thing that really helped me while I was a graduate student was reading about others who seem to have similar feelings.
So what I want to do here is explore those thoughts and feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;thoughts-and-feelings&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts and Feelings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am finding is there are a lot of those thoughts and feelings post-PhD.
In drafting this post, I found that I wanted to talk about EVERYTHING.
For this post alone, I thought about having sub-sections or digressions that talked about: finding personal validation through the structure of academia, feeling disconnected from academic peers as someone not going on to some fancy TT job this year, all the strange things people said at conferences last month, and this list goes on.
And in starting to sketch out what each of those digressions might look like, I realized here I had mountains of thoughts and feelings I wanted to share.
It was almost like that for every new fact I had learned in grad school, I was given two feelings to go along with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But given all these feelings, and no academic cohort anymore, who can I then share all these niche thoughts with?
This question becomes even more important when you consider that you really only are who you think you are in relation to other people.
I noticed this the most when I moved to London last year and didn’t have daily access to my cohort at Louisiana State Univeristy.
You don’t realize that you’re the “that guy” of your group until you leave them.
If you can’t define yourself as “the guy who really likes music theory and music cognition” in your new group, it’s like that part of you goes away as well.
This is a pretty big deal, because for many aspiring academics like myself, this is a huge part of our identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;crescendo&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Crescendo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the grim truth about this is realization is that post-PhD, these feelings might only increase with more time away from academic settings.
In a few weeks I am sure my &lt;code&gt;dbake29@lsu.edu&lt;/code&gt; email address will be disconnected.
I’ll move further away in many respects because I’m not taking that next logical career step of doing a post-doc, a VAP, or taking a “job”&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
In taking another path for right now, I will drift a bit further away from the rhythm of the academic year.
And in many ways, I have already started to experience this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past few Theory conferences I attended, the invevitalble “What are you doing next year?” question conversation always got a bit awkward when I told them that I didn’t have a “job” for next year.
Many times I felt compelled that I had to add some sort of caveat to my response saying that I was planning on applying for more “job”s next year, but next time with greater effort!
Though what made it the most weird, is that many people seemed almost not interested in what I was planning on doing this next year or, even worse, actually told me that if I did not take other work that was as close as possible no matter what to being a Music Theory professor, I was just shooting myself in the foot for the rest of my academic career.
This was off putting to say the least, but talking about this sad state of affairs is not a digression worth going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this whole situation brings up quite the conundrum.
As people move through the Ph.D system, not everyone who gets a Ph.D in [Insert Your Subject Here] is going to move on right away to a “job”.
If they don’t, the way things are currently set up they will start to spin a bit more out of the central orbit of the field.
At some point they might swing back in or they could drift off.
But it brings up what I think is an important question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the space look like for academics who are interested in all things academic, but don’t neatly fit into a comprehensible box of the current infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my PhD, conversations about this really didn’t come up as the part of any formalized curriculum.
And saw it coming.
Yet here I am.
Or more appropriately– here we are.
This group of people is only an ever growing population.
And will continue to be since it’s numerically impossible to place every person in a “job” each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;my-answer&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Answer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is a very large question and problem that exists far beyond that of Music Theory.
It might even be happening in Musicology as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But regardless, there ought to exist some sort of space for people who are card carrying academics without a clubhouse to return to.
And I guess what I want to start thinking out-loud about is thinking about what this kind of career diversity looks like that is not just academic purgatory or a career waiting room.
I want to try to think about establishing myself (and others) in this space.
And not just talk about it so it’s a bit more normal, but also write about what it might look like to enjoy being in this space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t really know what that will look like right now.
But in addition to all those thoughts and feelings that I want to talk about, I also have a lot of practical work I want to share.
And I think my twitter feed and website might be a good place to still stay in the loop and document experiences here or there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drafting up what I want to talk about post-Ph.D (even if it’s just for me to be therapeutic thoughts) I want to blog about career diversity, life as a graduate student, computational musicology, music science, how music theory relates to everything, and a whole host of other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So who knows.
I wanted to blog throughout much of my Ph.D, but just did not have the time.
Now on other side, I really want to explore all the topics I couldn’t justify while a grad student and use the whole process of a way as continuing to express my academic identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also add in a bit of fear that everyone that I talked to that left academia willingly said doing so was one of the best choices they’ve made in their life…&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For my non-academic readers, the “job” refers to a tenure track (TT) job in North America at a decent school near a city that you could imagine asking your partner to uproot their entire life so you can be a professor&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is going on in someone&#39;s head when they do melodic dictation?</title>
      <link>/talk/pedagogy-compmodel-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/pedagogy-compmodel-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s going on in someone&#39;s head when they do melodic dictation?</title>
      <link>/talk/mtmw-compmodel-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/mtmw-compmodel-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Frequency Facilitation Hypothesis</title>
      <link>/talk/againagain-ffh-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/againagain-ffh-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toynbee Hall Datathon</title>
      <link>/post/toynbee-hall-datathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/toynbee-hall-datathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;background&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone might be aware, but in addition to living that dissertation life this past year, I have also been volunteering at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toynbeehall.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Toynbee Hall&lt;/a&gt; as part of their newly re-started Residential Volunteer Worker program.
The program started WAY back in the late 1890s.
The idea was that all the bougie people from Oxbridge would come and live on-site in East London in order to do charity work and help out a bit before they were to go on to do other things like be elected to Parliament and then pass laws and help those that were not as well off.
I probably will not be elected to Parliament anytime soon, but will hopefully go on to be a helpful member of society in other ways.
Toynbee Hall restarted this program this past year and I was lucky enough to have my application accepted for the position.
Since then, I have been helping out as part of the research team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve helped out with a few smaller projects here or there (basically crunching the datasets they have and putting my other research skills to use doing interviews and what not), but before my year was up, I wanted to try and do my own mini-project which will be the focus of this post: a #data4good datathon at Toynbee Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/datathon-at-toynbee-hall-tickets-59760759039&#34;&gt;Check out the event and sign up here!!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;history-of-helping&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;History of Helping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read my glitzy description of the event in the link above, but if you’re reading my personal blog, as opposed to the event page, I assume this readership would want a bit more context on the Datathon and the ideas behind it.
To give a bit of background, Toynbee Hall is a very, very old charity based in East London.
It has a long history and was a touch point for a lot of important people in London back in the day who were interested in charity work (non-profit for all my North American readers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ages ago, some of the people here at Toynbee Hall helped out &lt;a href=&#34;https://booth.lse.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Charles Booth&lt;/a&gt; in his creation of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://booth.lse.ac.uk/map/14/-0.1174/51.5064/100/0&#34;&gt;London maps of poverty&lt;/a&gt; that essentially created the first data visualizations in what might be considered a #data4good cause.
Fast forward over 100 years and instead of going door to door and trying to use colors to highlight different levels of wealth on a map needing several panels, we can instead download publicly available data from something like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://theodi.org/&#34;&gt;Open Data Institute&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.london.gov.uk/&#34;&gt;The London Datastore&lt;/a&gt; and make data visualizations with the same goals in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given Toynbee Hall’s history and current research interests that engage the community by bringing different people together, it almost seemed like a no-brainer to try to put together something where we could try to combine all of these into one coherent event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;goals&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that there are community issues in need of addressing in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Borough_of_Tower_Hamlets&#34;&gt;Tower Hamlets&lt;/a&gt;, as well as community members who know the area, we wanted to continue in the tradition of bringing people together to answer a question.
Because my background has a bit of #rstats and data science (because of my work in music science), what seemed like the logical move here was to combine the history that Toynbee Hall has on data visualization and the local community using the data community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what were our goals in trying to do this event?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well the &lt;strong&gt;first&lt;/strong&gt; goal of this was to see what goes into organizing this kind of event.
I don’t really have too much of an event planning background and wanted to know what I would have to get in order to front load most of the data work for everyone.
This means gathering all the data to start with, figuring out how to best host it, and setting everyone up for success the afternoon of the event.
This data curation is most of what I do anyway, and I figured if this process did not prove too hard, then maybe I could help out remotely on events like this after I leave Toynbee in order to still be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt; goal is the most important one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to have the event result in the creation of meaningful material that Toynbee hall can use in their upcoming advocacy campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team is planning on looking at issues of both Youth Homelessness and Safety in Tower Hamlets this summer.
Any data that we could find and could include in future reports could really help provide evidence that could eventually be used in a policy campaign.
In order to do this we are using data that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yhdatabank.com/&#34;&gt;Centrepoint&lt;/a&gt; has given us, publicly available data on crime in London, and maybe one more source that I am putting together today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;third&lt;/strong&gt;, a by-product of having this event both locally and on Twitter, is to hopefully create some visibility to these issues.
Just having people tweeting their data visualizations and maybe having some be caught by the community at large would be great for making people aware of these issues.
It would also help us connect people who are interested in #data4good with charities or non-profits that they can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lastly&lt;/strong&gt;, in line with solving problems long term, I am also hoping to build up a network of people that Toynbee Hall can turn to after I leave.
The program that I am on is just one year long and I will go on to other work after this.
After my time here is up, I want to have linkd up the research team at Toynbee Hall with a network of people that could help in the future.
One way that we are hoping to accomplish this is take everyone that participates in our event and link them up with organizations like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datakind.org/chapters/datakind-uk&#34;&gt;DataKindUK&lt;/a&gt; and hopefully foster new relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a thousand other things I want to say about this event, but instead of editing more content that I originally drafted few weeks ago, I need to instead get all the content ready for us to go tomorrow.
I am sure I’ll be talking a lot more about this in the future when things calm down (still also on the come down from my dissertation submission last week…) but I invite you to join us tomorrow either at Toynbee (in the beautiful &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toynbeehall.org.uk/events/&#34;&gt;Ashbee Hall&lt;/a&gt;!) or online on Twitter with #data4toynbee and download the data from our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/research-at-toynbee-hall/datathons&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and help us out!
If you do download the data and something does not make sense, please @ me so I can fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to try it out now as I put on the finishing touches!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch if you want to chat more!
Either ping me on Twitter or send me an email!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sempre Grad Conference, 2019</title>
      <link>/post/sempre-grad-conference-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sempre-grad-conference-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I am planning on spending the whole day today writing, I figured: What better way to warm up to some writing than with some writing?&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
And what better way to get the juices flowing than to write about the wonderful experience that was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sempre.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Sempre&lt;/a&gt; graduate student conference at Cambridge this past Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this in North America, you might not be familiar with Sempre, so for the uninitiated, Sempre or the Society for Education, Music and Psychology Research is a professional organization in the UK dedicated towards bringing together those in various fields of music, but specifically music education and music psychology.
I don’t think we really have something like this in the USA.
The music psychology people tend to hang out at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.musicperception.org/&#34;&gt;Society for Music Perception and Cognition&lt;/a&gt;, and I am kind of embarrassed that off the top of my head I don’t know where graduate students in music education might submit research they are working on to present to their peers?
According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sempre.org.uk/about/1-background&#34;&gt;Sempre’s website&lt;/a&gt;, they’re very keen on helping out researchers at the start of their career and having this graduate conference is just one of the ways they do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference this week was a short and sweet one-day affair held at the Faculty of Music at Cambridge.
Of course the weather was perfect that day, but luckily all the talks made it worth it to sit indoors all day.
Ian Cross welcomed everyone with a short the opening address and if my memory serves me correctly, he noted there were about 80 submissions to this conference.
He said most of those submissions did happen to come the day of the deadline, which is quite in line with any stereotypes one may have about graduate students.
But thinking about that, I feel like if all professional music organizations were to release the timestamp data of their abstract submissions, there wouldn’t be a single one that didn’t exhibit an exponential growth in submissions in the hours leading to the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his short introduction, the keynote speaker Martin Rohrmeier, head of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dcml.epfl.ch/&#34;&gt;Digital and Computational Musicology Lab&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89cole_Polytechnique_F%C3%A9d%C3%A9rale_de_Lausanne&#34;&gt;École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne&lt;/a&gt; was introduced.
Martin’s talk surveyed a lot of his previous work on using computational tools to model various aspects of tonality which showcased the work of his graduate students in attendance that day.
He also presented an overview of his lab’s work looking at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/110/38/15443.full.pdf&#34;&gt;hierarchical, embedded structures within larger forms&lt;/a&gt;.
All of this empirical work then was tied together with what Martin put forward as a possible general theory of cognition and aesthetics that would be available to the listener, were they to choose, to engage deeply with a work of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing his audience as the next generation of music researchers, he made several pleas throughout his talk to encourage future work in music to work at the intersection between music theory, music psychology, and computer modeling.
This is an idea often gets poked at over here in Europe quite explicitly, but seems to live more as a tacit assumption in a lot of work in North America unless you’re at a talk by David Huron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the day took an ABA form with five minute flash talks surrounding a longer 12 minute talk session and the poster session scheduled for lunch.
As I tweeted earlier, I was skeptical of the five minute talks at first, thinking “How could people cram all they need to say into five minutes?!”&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but seeing as this was only a one-day conference that was more about community building rather than getting in the nitty gritty about methods, the format worked well.
Because of it, in a one-day session we were able to hear about the research of 20 graduate students on a diversity of topics (not even including the 25 posters at lunch!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost all of the talks in the morning session addressed issues at the intersection of music and well-being with the exception of a paper by Daniel Harasim looking at unsupervised machine learning methods to examine jazz harmonies.
Listening to all these talks only reiterated assertions made earlier in the keynote of how many human resources are needed in order to push knowledge limits in the field of music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start of the afternoon session was reminiscent of last summer’s multi-hub ICMPC conference as the winner of Sempre’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sempre.org.uk/awards/hickman&#34;&gt;Hickman&lt;/a&gt; award, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LAWarrenburg&#34;&gt;Lindsay Warrenbug&lt;/a&gt;, skyped into the conference to deliver her paper on Melancholy and Grief in Music.
It’s nice to see the music science community putting their money where their mouth is on making remote presentations a possibility for presenters (something also heavily advocated for by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/sysmusconference/&#34;&gt;SysMus Series&lt;/a&gt;).
Not to throw shade, but this is something that my home discipline of Music Theory needs to do a bit of catch-up on.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I look forward to the inevitable SMT Discuss or Twitter feud where we discuss if a person who can’t be to the national meeting in-person should instead be swapped out for someone who can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the talks in the afternoon were all extremely interesting.
It’s hard to go through and single out work I was loving since most of the work I liked was done by people who were good friends, but one paper that I feel like the theory and psychology community should be looking out for very soon was the work by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pmcharrison&#34;&gt;Peter Harrison&lt;/a&gt; and his advisor Marcus Pearce.
In 12 minutes, Peter was able to explain the current theories in the literature surrounding instantaneous consonance and dissonance (is it periodicity, is it spectral interference, is it cultural familiarity?), introduce an aggregated behavioral datasets from four prior studies where participants rated various sonorities, then introduce a new R package, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pmcharrison/incon&#34;&gt;“incon”&lt;/a&gt; that they used to computationally model 15 models of consonance to get to the bottom of the story.
If you’re interested in his findings, I know he also has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/6jsug/&#34;&gt;pre-print&lt;/a&gt; of it out right now.&lt;br /&gt;
I only mention his paper in detail because I think what he is doing is very in line with the music theory world and will hopefully start an interesting conversation once it gets published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the day we’d have heard talks on musical chills, emotions and music, using music to help rehabilitate stroke survivors, music’s role maternal mental health in The Gambia, and posters on topics from more traditional music theory (thinking about hierarchical voice leading structure ala Schenker with Graph Transformations) to decentering the dominant discourse of the ‘Dead White Men’ cannon.
It was a great day.
Not only did the conference have a diversity of talks, but of the 20 talks, there appeared to be 50/50 split in the gender of the speakers.
I only note that so when the inevitable “But is it even possible to have a conference where we just have men talk?!” question arise, there’s documentaiton of this happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to this conference and thinking about things like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://slate.com/technology/2019/03/google-doodle-bach-ai-music-generator.html&#34;&gt;general rage from last week regarding the Google Doodle&lt;/a&gt; made it very clear that there are many, many ways to do music research.
It made me wish that there were more conferences that follow this design beyond the graduate level.
I am only lamenting about this because if all goes well in May, this past Sempre conference will have been my last as a graduate student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this brings up ideas about the “point” of the conference, but one important “point” is that I don’t think conferences should just be be about apex research at its final moment of metamorphosis before publication.
I feel like we as researchers need more of a chance to air out our ideas in a less, shall I say… performative setting.
I obviously acknowledge that the content and subject matter with a conference like this is very different to that of AMS or SMT, but honestly think that the culture of something like Sempre is much closer to what people want and need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially true for early career researchers where point is to build relationships, explore new ideas, and not start to drink that academic Kool Aid right away since numerically speaking we will not all be academics, but will hopefully all engage in some kind of music research.
I’m also advocating for this because I’m currently in the peak of my PhD isolation phase now writing and going to this and being inspired by peers is what I think I’ll need to cross the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So big thanks to Sempre for hosting it, allowing for a day of intellectual curiosity, and continuing to grow a healthy network of next generation of researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;My thought yesterday morning, posting it a day later&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, an obvious personal projection&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which I only mention as personal grivence since I was not able to present some of my own work this year at a conference that I was not able to attend because of travel…&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Representations</title>
      <link>/post/digital-representations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/digital-representations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I obviously could not resist writing a blog post about yesterday’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/doodles/celebrating-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;Google Doodle&lt;/a&gt; twitter buzz.
I’m not going to try to talk about some of the smaller issues that came up.
And tons of people have already said &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@tompkinsguitar/googles-bach-ai-a-machine-learning-scientist-with-a-phd-in-music-theory-reacts-68d055f2461d?fbclid=IwAR1CuMvjwoAC1o0EPfBU5pa2mglRKp5BLcHpydh82HxHNktosxA3Ns7QgAg&#34;&gt;interesting things&lt;/a&gt;, but instead I’m hoping to ride the buzz so I can talk about something very relevant to the discussion: encoding and digital representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/imanimosley&#34;&gt;Imani Mosley&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imanimosley.com/humanistmachines/2019/3/21/breaking-the-doodle&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; as a jumping off point, she makes many great points about what Musicology twitter was interested in.
One thing that I was most struck by were claims the reason for the snark was the tired Bach-as-machine trope to explain why scientists gravitate to Bach.
In this post, I want to provide an alternative possibility of why researchers gravitate to Bach.
Researchers like Bach because it’s already encoded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Imani points out in her post, the dataset is made up from 308 compositions that the model was trained on.
You can read more about the model &lt;a href=&#34;https://magenta.tensorflow.org/coconet&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but each Chorale has many more musical events/data points.
Navigating to where the Bach chorales live on my computer and running the &lt;code&gt;census -k *.krn&lt;/code&gt; humdrum command on the first 308 of the Bach Chorales (just to ballpark) that were edited by Craig Sapp results in 72,030 note heads that can be analyzed with tools that can interpret &lt;code&gt;kern&lt;/code&gt; data.
This is a subset of 120,528 humdrum tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/digrep/kern1.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bring this up not to start debates about how much data is needed to train a model, but rather to point out that each little bit of data here had to be entered by hand for it to be used in any model.
And there is no way that you could get a model to even come close to output that would be interesting without very clean data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a researcher looking to tackle problems in this domain, having something like a complete set of Bach’s chorales in a digital format is a fantastic resource.
But one of the problems in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computational_musicology&#34;&gt;computational musicology&lt;/a&gt; is not the depth of data used to try to make a machine part-write in style of Bach, but rather the breadth of representation researchers can chose from when they pick which data to model.
How is it possible to make generalizable claims if you only look at a very small subset of music?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I work a lot with music and often use computers as a tool in that research.
Unlike the Bach problem here, I am interested in melodies, but the types of data and tools to analyze this data are similar.
One of the major problems I face in my work is that in order to make robust claims about music, you need to be able to show similar phenomena happen with new data.
But where does this new data come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a data scientist, you might get this from scraping a website or a government database.
If you’re a music psychologist, you often get data from experiments.
If you’re a computational musicologist, new data is not nearly as accessible.
Most likely, you need to either find some or create a digitized version of that data yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take the former option, you first inclination might be to go to somewhere like &lt;a href=&#34;http://kern.ccarh.org/&#34;&gt;kern scores&lt;/a&gt; or see what something like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://simssa.ca/&#34;&gt;SIMSSA project&lt;/a&gt; curates and to see what is available.
If you pop on over there for a second, you see a sample of what you can select from.
For the most part, it’s like a worse version of the old dead white dude problem that is being faced in both curricula and the performance world right now.
That said, there is still tons of data there.
Based on what is current there, the kern scores page has 7,866,496 notes from 108,703 files.
In addition to a lot of dead men, we also get a lot of folk songs, primarily with Hurons’s digitizing of Schaffrath’s work with the Essen collection.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
You’ll notice that there are not a lot of complete sets of lieder, full-on symphonies, or much new music (copyright and public domain are obviously also an issue).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take the latter option, you have to do encode these melodies yourself and digitizing music is not fun at all.
Over the past year, I encoded 778 monophonic melodies using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://musescore.org/en&#34;&gt;MuseScore&lt;/a&gt; platform.
These 778 melodies resulted in 36,387 notes, a vast majority of which I did personally.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
It sucked.
I hated having this giant encoding project living over my head throughout the dissertation writing process.
And since I am fresh out of it and still in peak bitter stage, thinking about this whole thing feels very much like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Little_Red_Hen&#34;&gt;a little red hen situation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, this kind of work could remain to be resigned to the individual.
Encoding a corpus could follow the lonely scholar in the ivory tower model where digitizing so much music is a sort of rite of passage.
But I don’t think that’s the best way forward for anyone involved.
I think encoding needs to be much more of a community effort and we can look to fields like psychology of how we as music-types might remedy this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in psychology, undergrad students taking psych courses in the USA are generally required to take part in experiments which generate the data for the papers that the field of psychology generally reads.
Using such restricted samples leads to problems in that this data is basically &lt;a href=&#34;https://slate.com/technology/2013/05/weird-psychology-social-science-researchers-rely-too-much-on-western-college-students.html&#34;&gt;WEIRD&lt;/a&gt;, but I think you could argue it’s better than not collecting any data.
In music, we don’t really have this problem as much because our research is not this-kind-of-data driven, nor should it in many topics.
But in cases like the one I’m describing here, we have our own litte weird problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remedy this, I imagine a world where in teaching music theory– where often competence in a computer notation is a learning objective– we spend a bit of time talking about this problem of (digital) representation in music.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
If every classroom were encodes some pop melodies (also a transcription exercise!), encode a Shostakovitch Fugue (a project I have been putting off for years now), or even encode one part of a symphony, all of this data would slowly start to accumulate for anyone to model.
Doing this would lead to a deluge of new data for researchers to use, allow for Meyerian comparisons between styles, and teach students about serious pressing problems in research while having them learn about notational software.
This also will expose them to the field of computational musicology, something that I didn’t even know existed until half-way through my Masters in &lt;em&gt;psychology&lt;/em&gt;.
Additionally, once compositions cross into the public domain, we as a research community can work towards having more music, more accessible to more people in the form of open scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it could be that there is this tired trope of Bach-as-machine (which certainly plays into it), but I’d be interested to know how much of what we do is just by-products of the means we have to answer those questions.
Either way, as noted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Komaniecki_R/status/1108825660653473792&#34;&gt;Robert Komaniecki&lt;/a&gt;, hats off to the Google team for getting people to get so fired up about part-writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schaffrath, H. (1995). The Essen Folksong Collection in Kern Format. [computer database]. D. Huron (ed.). Menlo Park, CA: Center for Computer Assisted Research in the Humanities, 1995.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple of my LSU colleagues helped out on some of them.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also a great place to talk about human biases in algorithms, the need to be ethical in research…&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#wikiwednesday</title>
      <link>/post/wikiwednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wikiwednesday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest issues that I lament about regarding Twitter is how there is so much great information just falling through my feed, never to be recovered again.
A perfect example of this appeared yesterday when &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/willmasonmusic&#34;&gt;Will Mason&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/willmasonmusic/status/1105462217728761857&#34;&gt;tweeted asking for people to help provide examples of idiomatic instrumental constraints leading to funny pitch choices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/wiki_20190313_post/will_tweet.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within one day, there were loads examples of this along with some discussion contextualizing the responses.
Examples like this happen all the time on Twitter ranging from people needing specific musical examples to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DougShadle/status/1066802040217759744&#34;&gt;killer Twitter rants like this one&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DougShadle&#34;&gt;Doug Shadle&lt;/a&gt; that took me way too long to find, which only proves my point.
After liking the tweets, that’s usually where my engagement with the information ends, then I get sad that this information will never be available again for anyone who was not on Twitter yesterday.
I know it lives on Twitter and can dig it out, but I honestly feel I should be spending less time on my computer when I find myself telling more senior music scholars things like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, actually, there was a really good Twitter thread about this the other day”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can be done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, one thing that I think a lot of people forget about is that all this information can and should be put on Wikipedia.
After looking at Will’s thread, I put “Idiomatic Music” in the Wikipedia search bar, and was directed to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instrumental_idiom&#34;&gt;stub of a page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/wiki_20190313_post/pre_edit.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I would have hoped to find the information on Will’s tweet if I were looking for it on another day, but it’s not there.
So in true “knowledge should be for everyone” fashion, I added it to the page and thought this might be a good opportunity to procrastinate writing my dissertation by writing a blog about my favorite dissertation writing procrastination activity: editing Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;editing-wikipedia&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Editing Wikipedia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I have been meaning to blog about, and this obviously has given me a good reason to, is how easy and important I think it is for academics to edit Wikipedia.
It’s so important that I have even turned my love of editing Wikipedia into something I personally refer to as #wikiwednesday.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, #wikiwednesday is just a weekly reminder that I should add something to Wikipedia every Wednesday.
For the past few weeks, I have been doing it on topics related to my dissertation, but in this post I honestly wanted to show how easy it is to edit Wikipedia for anyone that hasn’t yet.
Hopefully after seeing a few screenshots, you too will be inclined to help out as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that you need to do is make an account.
I made a quick one just for this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/wiki_20190313_post/make_account.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, now with an account made, the next thing that you need to do is click the Edit Source button found in the top right corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/wiki_20190313_post/editsource.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here (at least my my Firefox?) there’s the option to use the Visual Editor mode.
If you’re not familiar with Markdown and HTML and what not, this is the way to go in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/wiki_20190313_post/viz_editor.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, this opens up the hood and you can start editing.
I am personally in the process of doing the last 50 days of my dissertation, so I seriously do not have time to restructure this page, but I do have time to add in a bit of text (and do this quick blog post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, all I wanted to do was create a new heading that would provide some examples of this, then write some very OK text with some concrete examples from Will’s thread.
The text is not poetic by any means, but it’s better for it to be there than not.
And if you think what I wrote sucks, you can always change it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adding all this in, I then tried to link in some of the composers and examples with the link tool.
It might take a second to get a handle of how this works, but it’s time well spent in my opinion.
After a few minutes of editing….&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instrumental_idiom&#34;&gt;Tah Dah!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wiki-ing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;wiki-ing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of me wanted to just keep going and adding to this page, but my hope is that people will read this post and do a bit of their own #wikiwednesday-ing and just try to do one small edit on this page or another.
I find that once you start, I think it’s pretty fun and actually kind of hard to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is it fun (my opinion), but I also think that if you are an expert in something (cougheveryonewithaphdcough), you have a responsibility to edit Wikipedia in your own subject area.
Not only is it important to give people up-to-date and accurate information, but Wikipedia is also a place where most people probably start most of their inquiries.
And this isn’t just undergrads, the amount of times I have seen people crack open Wikipedia on their phones at an SMT or AMS talk on a subject outside of their realm of expertise is pretty funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I think this is so important is because this writing will be more read than any article I write in any journal (especially if it’s written behind a pay wall!) and probably have more of a cumulative impact than most of my research.
Also, knowing that Wikipedia is probably the best empirical evidence of what we as a community canonize, it becomes so important to make sure that Wikipedia is representative of the world we want to exist in.
I’m obviously not the first by any means to point this out.
There has recently been coverage of Wikipedia’s diversity issues by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/style/history-has-a-massive-gender-bias-well-settle-for-fixing-wikipedia/2019/02/15/b2537640-3163-11e9-86ab-5d02109aeb01_story.html?utm_term=.72aa4b49348f&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; and anyone that is not living under a rock (aka not on Twitter) knows that the music community is actively working towards &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.annakijas.com/rebalancing-the-music-canon/&#34;&gt;Rebalancing the Music Canon&lt;/a&gt; as blogged about by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/anna_kijas&#34;&gt;Anna Kijas&lt;/a&gt; and working towards more accessibility of music from historically under-represented composers by initiatives like &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MTEW_com&#34;&gt;Music Theory Examples by Women&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ComposerProject&#34;&gt;The Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt;.
All I am trying to get across with this post is how important I see it for anyone with skin in the game to take a bit of time out of their day each week and make a habit out of putting information out where most people read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this is being done too, I guess I just am hoping for more of it.
I’ve seen that some people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/K_Leonard_PhD&#34;&gt;Kendra Leonard&lt;/a&gt; starting to organize Wikipedia sessions (couldn’t find this exact tweet to link in?) to create and edit pages on Women composers.
In my opinion, if both &lt;a href=&#34;https://societymusictheory.org/&#34;&gt;SMT&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsmusicology.org/&#34;&gt;AMS&lt;/a&gt; put aside 2 hours each national conference to edit the music pages of Wikipedia, we as a society could take most of the year off of #publicmusicology (just kidding, but maybe not because that level of human resources editing Wikipedia would be unheard of).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on that note, I think it’d be nice if anyone interested in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23publicmusicology&amp;amp;src=typd&#34;&gt;#publicmusicology&lt;/a&gt; would join me in my weekly small edits of Wikipedia and share small portions of what they did with #wikiwednesday to remind others to also help out.
Or you could get back to devoting all your time to that article that most people probably will not read (#shotsfired).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;My love for editing Wikipedia pages grew out of taking extensive notes on a server that my advsior, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/danielshanahan&#34;&gt;Dan Shanahan&lt;/a&gt; set one up for our department to facilitate collective knowledge for our department.
Of course those posts live in on a “private” wiki, but they will one day see the light of day when I either blog about them or try to get all that info to Wikipedia.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cataloging Memories with Music</title>
      <link>/post/cataloging-memories-with-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cataloging-memories-with-music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few times that I have sat down to work on my dissertation I have run into a writer’s block.
Though it is not the kind of writer’s block where nothing comes out.
The past few times I have set aside time to write I have had &lt;em&gt;so many&lt;/em&gt; thoughts that I have not been able to just stick my nose to the ground and write.
My brain feel like it’s on fire.
It’s the end of the year and it has been an intense one and it’s important to acknowledge that.
Too often in grad school we work and work and work and work, and never reflect on how we even ended up in this situation in the first place.
There is too much doing and not enough reflecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to attend to that problem, as opposed to just tweet about how we need a change of culture (but really be frantically work on yet another manuscript) I set aside some time yesterday to write about something I have been wanting to share for a while: my auto-biographical musical playlists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;darling&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Darling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general background and inspiration from this post and idea comes from some music science literature investigating how music has the power to evoke strong emotional memories that are not related to the structure of the music itself.
There has been some cool work on it that you can read about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09658210701734593&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/55ac0a53e4b05f2993b25780/t/55c9ffdde4b0e9393a61707c/1439301597483/Belfi_etal_2015_Memory.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that digs into it properly, which also runs in tandem with research suggesting why &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24006129&#34;&gt;really like the music we listened to in our formative years.&lt;/a&gt;
But for all the intents and purposes of this post, all you really have to know is that there is good evidence to suggest that a strong link exists between music and memories of specific moments in our lives.
Ages ago, when I first started getting into music science I heard this referred to as the “Darling, they are playing our song!” effect and &lt;strong&gt;I wanted to see if I could use some of this research in my own life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as a result of reading about this area of research in music science, a few years ago I decided to start keeping a playlist diary on Spotify.
The idea of it was that I would add a song to the playlist whenever I had a strong experience associated with music.
The experiences did not have to be exact mappings such as this exact song must be playing during a certain moment for it to be added to my playlist; the idea was that any memory that might be bottled up in a song could get added as not to make the inclusion criteria that strict.
This of course is naturally much easier for a musicophile like myself who basically always has music playing or is around music.
All that needed to happen was for me to be a bit more mindful as I went about my life.
If a song comes on that seems like it is painting a nice soundscape to the backdrop of my life, it gets added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have been running this experiment on myself for the past four years.
It’s the end of 2018 now, so what got added to it this year?
Here is a link to the playlist itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/user/1220215602/playlist/3rfnbRTo1WVReR4exGvNjE&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I am writing this post I have been listening to the playlist and, like the past few years, when listening to it, I get immediately transported back to the memories I actively chose to catalog.
The first couple of songs take me right back to celebrating the New Year with my friends in Baton Rouge.
For example, I remember the second tune, Lambada, coming on the radio as my friends drove to buy food to make breakfast after a long weekend in New Orleans.
The moment felt right, so I whipped out my phone to Shazam the tune, and then later added it to my list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3F7HdGevVojxdsARD4RHad&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just exact moments that I catalog, but I also record re-occurring songs.
For example, later on the list is some Debussy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/00IZ3ndf3TNXt3hMum4WAV&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the music, but more importantly it’s used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westworld_(TV_series)&#34;&gt;Westworld&lt;/a&gt; and I used to have weekly Sunday screenings of the show at my apartment in Baton Rouge.
I wanted to remember sitting quietly in a room with my friends having a bit of a break before Monday would come up and grad school would restart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;patterns&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Patterns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I’d like to look at the list and maybe see some patterns over a lifetime.
For example, I’d imagine that more songs/memories would cluster around highly anticipated emotional events.
I saw this play out last year with two salient songs from my PhD General Exams.
The first example is this great tune my friend Crystal put on in my living room after a day of drinking celebrating being done with three days of writing for the first part of our General Exams and learning the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uwJ66XxGBFk&#34;&gt;line dance&lt;/a&gt; to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/42excP3MyVua6modv3v9Pz&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a few weeks and the night before my oral defense, I remember sitting in a Sonic parking lot eating ice cream with my friends Sasha and Jacob, listening to Eye of the Tiger at full volume.
It was a moment where it felt like God had momentarily DJ’d for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2KH16WveTQWT6KOG9Rg6e2&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cruising through this playlist I also realize how much traveling I did this year and all the great people I got to hang out with.
Just weeks after Eye of the Tiger, I got to hang out at a public musicology conference in South Carolina and ended up hanging out with both &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/darkmusictheory?lang=en&#34;&gt;darkmusictheory&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/12tonevideos?lang=en&#34;&gt;12tone&lt;/a&gt; late at night in an AirBnB and remember really liking the piano intro to this tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4L1eqdFY10yO7tMzvRp0sx&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of my playlist comes from memories traveling.
In Florida I remember sitting with my friend Rory while talking about how we are spending our lives and this recording of &lt;em&gt;A Mi Manera&lt;/em&gt; came on the radio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0Nx5c4i2z90wi8Uj6LbUbH&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first vacation/holiday I had ever taken just for the sake of a vacation (not academic work related) in years and I distinctly remember sitting on the patio, asking the server to start happy hour early, mis-ordering our 2 for 1 margaritas, then both being served 2 drinks at 2PM and boozing it up in full Jimmy Buffet regalia.
Of course I won’t go on a play by play&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of my whole list, but the meaningful thing is that as a whole this playlist only ‘makes sense’ to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone looking at the playlist might be able to figure out some of the tunes given that they knew where I was at what time such as this recording added at the start of July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1b7kLkJkr6XRYgWqVmDm05&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other songs that I have known for a while get emotionally recycled and obtain new meaning just for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6pGEheBKHMS6cvYqqKcU6O&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;zooming-out&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Zooming Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the cool thing is, as I mentioned above, I have been doing this for the past four years.
Going all the way back to 2015 I can still vividly transport myself back to eating donuts in an NYC apartment listening to Laura Mvula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6VKhTOUK905auFiINtfLZZ&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even as the 2015 playlist plays, I still anticipate each song within this playlist’s context with each memory being anticipated as well.
So what I guess I am basically suggesting is that on a personal level, if you have an assortment of external musical meaning your life, maybe it is time to consider starting an autobiographical musical memories playlist yourself in 2019?
I have found knowing that this playlist is there helps me stay more present when music is playing (which is a lot of the time) since you never know if a moment will meet your inner arbitrary threshold for adding it to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also be interested to know if anyone after reading this does go ahead and do it.
I’d be very keen to have an intense music psychology conversation about similarities in partaking in this activity.
I’ve also linked here the past four years just for proof, but also want to show off how diverse this kind of playlist can get since it’s not bound by anything like genre, style, mood, or some sort of lyrical similarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/user/1220215602/playlist/2Ndu7gNgVs1KFMUB4rjoA9&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/user/1220215602/playlist/7kA7U2jeQIMzJjvhU8knhs&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/user/1220215602/playlist/5Gb4jiSS6ikyEJOgpemxn6&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/embed/user/1220215602/playlist/3rfnbRTo1WVReR4exGvNjE&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pun intended&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Melodic Dictation</title>
      <link>/talk/open-university-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/open-university-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Musical Sophistication</title>
      <link>/post/examining-musical-sophistication/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/examining-musical-sophistication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;replication&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Replication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://davidjohnbaker.rbind.io/post/examining-musical-sophistication/&#34;&gt;Replication&lt;/a&gt;.
Is it popular and important for research in psychology?
Yes.
Will reading a replication paper get you all fired up about research?
Probably not.
That’s OK though, research really shouldn’t be all about new and flashy findings.
Every so often we should stop and think about what we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today our lab has a new publication “Examining Musical Sophistication: A replication and theoretical commentary on the Goldsmiths Musical Sophistication Index” that’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/eprint/qwVM6dhD6ipcWM4XAacv/full&#34;&gt;accessible online&lt;/a&gt; that replicates the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0089642&#34;&gt;Goldsmiths Musical Sophistication Index&lt;/a&gt;.
The “just-tell-me-if-I-can-keep-using-it” verdict of the paper is: “Yes, knock yourself out”.
Scroll to the bottom of the page, grab the APA citation and cite us as Baker, Ventura, Calamia, Shanahan, and Elliott (2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re keen on psychometrics and are interested in a few of the points we make in the paper, then read on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give the very short version of the paper in plain English (not abstract-ese) the paper generally goes like this.
Over the past century the world of music science has struggled to quantify what it means to be musical.
We clearly need some measure of it if we want to make claims about how much engaging with music relates to other constructs, but every time you try to pin down what you think being musical is, you realize you forgot something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;measuring-musicality&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Measuring Musicality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have tried to get around this problem a few different ways, but in this paper we decided to focus on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0089642&#34;&gt;Goldsmiths Musical Sophistication Index&lt;/a&gt; since it’s a tool that has getting very popular, very quickly within the music science world and had previously been shown to be valid and reliable in a large UK sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for the paper came from a lab meeting one day at LSU where we were discussing open science and our own research practices, and how we wanted to participate in this important movement.
Given the resources we had at the time, we decided it would be a good idea to investigate the replicability of the Gold-MSI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a couple of specific reasons for this as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most researchers are not going to be using samples like that in the original paper (N= 147,000+) and will probably just use it on their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20550733&#34;&gt;WEIRD&lt;/a&gt; subject pool, therefore we should investigate if there are any “weird” things that happen when you use it like this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some researchers break off a part of the Gold-MSI and use just one of the sub scales; is that a good idea?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An independent replication of the Gold-MSI would be a valuable contribution and it’d be good to write a paper that might be helpful for others to read and cite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had also just read this great paper on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1047840X.2016.1153946&#34;&gt;Process Overlap Theory&lt;/a&gt; and saw a lot of parallels between what Kovacs and Conway had to say when arguing against the idea of &lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt; and the idea of measuring anything musical with a latent variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we went ahead, grabbed us some data, and spent a lot of time reading Alex Beaujean’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Latent-Variable-Modeling-Using-R/dp/1848726996&#34;&gt;Latent Variable Analysis with R&lt;/a&gt; book to dive deep into the world of latent variable modeling.
So what did we find?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;practice&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the Gold-MSI pretty much behaved as you would expect it to.
Using a WEIRD sample, we had a bit of a skewed distribution that people should look out for, but the sub-scale scores pretty much lined up with the means and standard deviations that were originally reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Figure1_GMSIREP.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overall Skew&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Overall Skew&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Figure2_GMSIREP.png&#34; alt=&#34;Similar Descriptive Statistics&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Similar Descriptive Statistics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, we did look at the item level data and found anything but normal distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Figure3_GMSIREP.png&#34; alt=&#34;Item Level Distributions&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Item Level Distributions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the biggest deal in the world due to the estimators you can use with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lavaan.ugent.be/&#34;&gt;lavaan package&lt;/a&gt; that were used in the original paper, but if you are going to break off a scale to use just a part of the Gold-MSI, it’s worth keeping in mind.
We noted the biggest problems with this using the Emotion sub-scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also show have &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of tables in the paper that go over everything from descriptive statistics to model fits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;theory&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given our generally successful replication, is there anything else researchers should know?
We we zoomed out a bit (from painfully up close to the Gold-MSI) and expanded outwards in our discussion.
In the paper we highlighted that the Gold-MSI uses latent variables, which basically relies on the same math as calculating &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G_factor_(psychometrics)&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
The construct &lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt; is calculated using a bunch of objective tests that correlate with one another, but you still use factor analytic techniques to derive the larger constructs, in this case the General Sophistication score and its sub scales (actually it is even fancier than that since they use &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02289209&#34;&gt;a bifactor solution&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After pointing this out we draw upon a few arguments made by Kovacs and Conway and argued that even though someone might score highly on some of the Gold-MSI scales, it doesn’t mean that they are using their “musical sophistication” to actually carry out musical tasks.
Just like you wouldn’t say you used your general intelligence to solve a mental rotation puzzle, you wouldn’t say you used your musical sophistication to do a melodic memory task.
We note that this is great for descriptive theories, but we just want to remind people that they shouldn’t confuse a statistical abstraction for any sort of process that is actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get a lot more fanciful with the language in the article, but hopefully you’ll give it a read if you’ve gotten this far in the blog post.
The paper ends saying that people should of course keep using the Gold-MSI as we desperately need more consistency in measurements, but as a community we need to think about what our models are actually telling us.
This is especially true in that we are now coming up on the 100 year anniversary of Seashore’s Measures of Musical Talents and it’s a perfect time to stop and reflect on the tools we are using and the questions we are trying to ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds up your alley, give the paper a read.
You can access it &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/eprint/qwVM6dhD6ipcWM4XAacv/full&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and if you’d like to cite us, just copy and paste below!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re big proponents of collaborating, sharing data, and being transparent, so if anyone wants to get their hands on our data and analysis, please get in touch and check out our lab’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/cdqm5/&#34;&gt;OSF page&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also a big thanks to our reviewers!
The paper was of much higher quality after the suggestions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baker, D. J., Ventura, J., Calamia, M., Shanahan, D., &amp;amp; Elliott, E. M. (2018). Examining musical sophistication: A replication and theoretical commentary on the Goldsmiths Musical Sophistication Index. Musicae Scientiae. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/1029864918811879&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/1029864918811879&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Musical Sophistication: A replication of the Goldsmiths Musical Sophistication Index</title>
      <link>/publication/gmsi-replication-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gmsi-replication-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding emotions in expressive music performance: A multi-lab replication and extension study</title>
      <link>/publication/emotion-replication-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/emotion-replication-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
