<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on David John Baker</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on David John Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 David John Baker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Musicologists on Twitter</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-15-counting-amsmt-tweets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-15-counting-amsmt-tweets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the most part, Twitter is full of garbage.
But I&amp;rsquo;m an optimist and a firm believer in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturgeon%27s_law&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sturgeon&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/a&gt; so by that logic there must be some good on it.
That good is academic twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is not a post meaning to talk about how great academic twitter is, I did want to write a quick post to
1. see if I could write a blog post using blogdown&amp;rsquo;s markdown and
2. share how I scraped twitter to find active users in the Musicology and Music Theory community&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it goes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that you have to do is get some tweets.
Luckily there are some great packages out there in the #rstats world that can help with this.
For this project I used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/twitteR/twitteR.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;twitteR&lt;/a&gt; package which lets you log into Twitter&amp;rsquo;s API.
There are already some great instructions on how to get started with it that you can find &lt;a href=&#34;https://davetang.org/muse/2013/04/06/using-the-r_twitter-package/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, so I won&amp;rsquo;t go into tons of detail about some of that code is doing.
Also you can&amp;rsquo;t just copy and paste my code since it requires credentials from your own Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Musicologists on Twitter</title>
      <link>/post/looking-for-musicologists-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/looking-for-musicologists-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the most part, Twitter is full of garbage. But I’m an optimist and a firm believer in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturgeon%27s_law&#34;&gt;Sturgeon’s Law&lt;/a&gt; so by that logic there must be some good on it. That good is academic twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is not a post meaning to talk about how great academic twitter is, I did want to write a quick post to 1. see if I could write a blog post using blogdown’s markdown and 2. share how I scraped twitter to find active users in the Musicology and Music Theory community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here it goes…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that you have to do is get some tweets. Luckily there are some great packages out there in the #rstats world that can help with this. For this project I used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/twitteR/twitteR.pdf&#34;&gt;twitteR&lt;/a&gt; package which lets you log into Twitter’s API. There are already some great instructions on how to get started with it that you can find &lt;a href=&#34;https://davetang.org/muse/2013/04/06/using-the-r_twitter-package/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, so I won’t go into tons of detail about some of that code is doing. Also you can’t just copy and paste my code since it requires credentials from your own Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s first load the two packages we’ll need&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(data.table)
library(twitteR)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>/post/2017-08-26-hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-08-26-hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post on my fresh, new website.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been off the world of blogging for quite some time, but will hopefully be populating this site with all things music and science in the near future.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to create content relevant to what it&amp;rsquo;s like to do research in music science and help anyone out who is interested in learning more about anything from graduate school life, to computational musicology, to music psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for visiting for now and hope to see you soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
