<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on David John Baker</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on David John Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 David John Baker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part IV</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-iv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-iv/</guid>
      <description>Since this is my last post in the beer review series, I’ll keep this short and sweet in terms of analysis. Having done all of this, I do have a few reflections I would like to share after doing the One-Size-Fits-All-Data-Science Interview that I have included at the end.
Our final question to answer is:
 Lastly, if I typically enjoy a beer due to its aroma and appearance, which beer style should I try?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part III</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-datascientist-part-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-datascientist-part-iii/</guid>
      <description>Two questions down, two to go! For the third post I’ll explore the question:
 Which of the factors (aroma, taste, appearance, palate) are most important in determining the overall quality of a beer?
 Whereas the posts before were questions on sorting data, this is our first attempt to make some statistical models. In this case, we’re going to be doing a bit of regression modeling.
There are a couple of ways to tackle this problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part II</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on from my earlier post, I’m now looking to tackle the question:
 If you had to pick 3 beers to recommend using only this data, which would you pick?
 This is a pretty open ended question, which is kind of fun. I also don’t really have a ton of experience (yet!) in recommendation systems, though I have done a little reading here or there on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me (as a Data Scientist!), Part I</title>
      <link>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hire-me-as-a-data-scientist-part-i/</guid>
      <description>Background I read Medium blog posts on “How to Become a Data Scientist” more often than I care to admit. Much of this comes from a fear that after doing all this work on the PhD and then hitting the Music Theory job market, I won’t fit the mold of the kind of theorist most schools want to hire. Not coming from one of five schools that seem to have a monopoly on the tenure track jobs can be a bit discouraging, but I also won’t deny that having a non-academic job with a regular 9-5 schedule and a decent salary is pretty tempting after spending the vast majority of my twenties in school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking For Musicologists on Twitter</title>
      <link>/post/looking-for-musicologists-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/looking-for-musicologists-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>For the most part, Twitter is full of garbage. But I’m an optimist and a firm believer in Sturgeon’s Law so by that logic there must be some good on it. That good is academic twitter.
While this isn’t a post advocating for academic Twitter, I did want to
1. see if I could figure out how to write a post with some R code in it and 2. share how I scraped Twitter to find active users in the Musicology and Music Theory community</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calculating iMultisets in R</title>
      <link>/post/calculating-imultisets-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/calculating-imultisets-in-r/</guid>
      <description>November is pretty much the worst month for people in higher education. There are too many deadlines and if you’re still in coursework (like myself) you have essays to write, presentations to make, and a backlog of homework assignments to grade. So if you can save time here or there, it’s usually a good choice.
This weekend I was working a homework assignment for my Transformational Theory seminar where we were given a number of pairs of pitch class sets and had to calculate the imultiset for each following Joseph Straus’ 2014 article on Total Voice Leading.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>