<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on David John Baker</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on David John Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 David John Baker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Music Industry</title>
      <link>/project/music-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/music-industry/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In addition to academic work, I&amp;rsquo;m also often involved as working as a consultant for various music industry projects.
One of the great things about working in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23musicscience&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;#musicscience&lt;/a&gt; is that there is a bit more opportunity to do consultancy work where theory can meet practice.
If you&amp;rsquo;d like to hire me for anything from trying to find insight from your dirty data, to making data products, to scientific consultancy, please don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:davidjohnbaker1@gmail.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of projects that I have been involved with in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;projects&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;soundscape&#34;&gt;Soundscape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer I am currently involved on a project with &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundscapeagency.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Soundscape Agency&lt;/a&gt; acting as their scientific consultant to help develop music in collaboration with various artists from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasedtapes.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Erased Tapes&lt;/a&gt; record label.
More information to come soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;soundout&#34;&gt;Soundout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.soundout.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Soundout&lt;/a&gt;, I worked on a project with their lead data scientist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/tabitha-trahan/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tabi Trahan&lt;/a&gt; and Dr. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doc.gold.ac.uk/~mas03dm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Daniel Müllensifen&lt;/a&gt; to develop a tool that mapped Music and Brand personality onto the same emotional space.
The details of the project can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/306374399_Matching_Music_to_Brand_Personality_A_Semantic_Differential_Tool_for_Measuring_Emotional_Space&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Music Perception and Cognition&lt;/a&gt;.
The tool served as the basis for what later became their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.soundout.com/brandmatch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BrandMatch&lt;/a&gt; tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;audio-branding-academy&#34;&gt;Audio Branding Academy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I presented with Dr. Daniel Müllensifen at the Audio Branding Academy annual conference in Berlin, Germany.
We gave a half-day workshop on tools that help bridge gaps between academics, creatives, and industry minded people.
A summary of our workshop can be found in their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284721150_Music_Brands_Advertising_Testing_What_Works&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;annual yearbook from that year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Musicology</title>
      <link>/project/computational-musicology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/computational-musicology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Computational Musicology involves using computers to digitize musical data and then using powerful software to search through massive amounts of data that would be unfeasible to do by hand. I am particularly interested in using symbolic data to extract information from melodies that can be used to predict how well melodies are remembered and creating new data sets that others can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One project involving creating new datasets involves curating a dataset of improvised jazz solos.
In its current state, the corpus is encoded in **kern and has solos from Charlie Parker (~70), Clifford Brown (~80), as well as Dizzy Gillespie (~10).
We are in the process of including data from Miles Davis, John Coltrane, as well as other artists.
Though not publicly availible yet, the dataset will have both melodic as well as harmonic information and be easily indexed using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.humdrum.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Humdrum&lt;/a&gt; tool kit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music Cognition and Computation Lab</title>
      <link>/project/lsu-lab-external/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/lsu-lab-external/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music and Memory</title>
      <link>/project/music-and-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/music-and-memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My main research interest investigates what individual and musical factors contribute to how someone learns and remembers a melody.
Not only do findings in this area have relevance for music perception, but they also have  implications for how aural skills are taught at the conservatory level of music education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the initial findings from our research are going to be published in the upcoming conference proceedings for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://music-psychology-conference2018.uni-graz.at/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;International Conference for Music Perception and Cognition&lt;/a&gt; and are serving as the basis for my dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
